בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, so today's דף *daf* is דף ל *Daf
Lamed*, starting from the bottom of כז עמוד ב *Kaf-Zayin Amud Bet*.
And just to remind everybody, we have this very specific constructive scenario
of a woman who appears in front of us, the rabbis, wants
to know what her story is. She had a miscarriage sometime in
the past. She doesn't know when, between today and some months ago,
so she doesn't even know, she doesn't know what her status is.
And the issue here then, and we have set up the scenario
that she does not bleed for three weeks, and then every other
week she bleeds for a full week all through fourteen weeks. God
forbid this case never happen in real life, but it gives the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* an opportunity to explore
the extent of the application of some of the principles. So the
question here is two questions: number one, when can she, is she
טהורה tehorah, *tehorah*? When can she definitely know she's טהורה tehorah, *tehorah*
during this term? And when can she have sex with her husband?
We explained. And also number two, assuming a position that טבילה בזמנה
מצוה Tevilah Bizmanah Mitzvah, *tevilah bizmanah mitzvah*, that you have to go
to the מקווה mikvah. *mikvah* the very first moment you have an
opportunity to,
then how many times would this woman have to go to the
מקווה mikvah *mikvah*? Because we don't know how טמאה *temeah* she's been,
when she becomes טהורה tehorah. *tehorah*, and every single time there's a
possibility she'll have to go to the מקווה mikvah *mikvah* that that
is her day that she becomes able to go to the מקווה
mikvah *mikvah*, she goes to the מקווה mikvah *mikvah*. So the ברייתא
braitah *Beraita* said that the only time in this entire period that
she can have sex with her husband is this night, the night
leading into the thirty-sixth day of this entire whatever it is, ninety-one
days period. And it also said that according to בית שמאי Beis
Shammai *Beit Shammai*, she goes to the מקווה mikvah *mikvah* ninety-five times,
and according to בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel*, she goes to
the מקווה mikvah *mikvah* thirty-five times. So just to review what we
said yesterday
about why this is the one day she goes to the מקווה
*mikvah*, the one day she's with her husband, and then the real
focus today is going to be how many times she goes to
the מקווה *mikvah*. Why is this the one day? These are weeks
here, one, two, three, four, five, six, seven. Why is this the
one day she goes to the מקווה *mikvah*? Well, the first three
weeks, although she hasn't bled at all, she can't go to the
מקווה *mikvah*, why? She might have had a childbirth, and a childbirth
for a girl would be two weeks. Okay, why at the three
weeks she's not bleeding, why can't she be with her husband then?
Well, because if she was also a זבה Zavah *zavah* and she
gave childbirth, and if we assume the ruling that you cannot count
the days of טומאה Tumah, *tumah* for a childbirth, the week or
the two weeks if it's a girl, even if there's no bleeding
towards זבה Zavah *zavah*, then she hasn't had her seven clean days
for זבה Zavah *zavah*. So you have to wait seven clean days.
So until this period she has to assume worst case is she
had a baby girl and she's a זבה Zavah *zavah*, needs three
weeks. Okay, now how about going to the מקווה *mikvah* tonight? How
about going to the מקווה *mikvah* now and having sex with her
husband this night? No, you can't do that, sorry, because now you're
bleeding. This is a day that she's constantly bleeding, we're assuming the
bleeding starting on the twenty-second day. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually goes
through a lot of why it couldn't be earlier, but anyway, we'll
go over that later. Okay, so now she's bleeding here, so she's
bleeding, this is definitely, and so she's bleeding here,
so she could go to the מקווה
*mikvah*...
let me just check this real quick.
So at the end of the seven days, right, she's bleeding נדה
Niddah *niddah*, right. I'm just trying to figure out why,
no no no, I'm wrong, that's
why it's not working.
Yes, seven times seven, exactly.
It is before day thirty-five, but that's here, it's not here. Okay,
thank you. Okay, so she's bleeding, right, it is day thirty-five, but
that's the day thirty-five. So she's bleeding, this bleeding makes her נדה
Niddah *niddah*, okay. She's clearly a נדה Niddah, *niddah*. But נדה Niddah
*niddah*, why didn't we just say נדה niddah *niddah* and clear it?
Except basically at the outset, well because all of this might be
during her טוהר *tohar* period of a childbirth. So again, the worst-case
scenario is, or the possibility is, that this starts נדה niddah *niddah*
and all
this was during the טוהר *tohar* period. Then she's טמאה *temeah* for
a week. If it was
a boy or girl, at least forty days, in fact yet eighty
days. So maybe this eighty days ends here, okay. So this is
the beginning of נדה niddah. *niddah*, that's the beginning of נדה niddah.
*niddah*, she's טמאה *temeah* from שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* until Friday, okay, and
then finally here, worst case was this was a נדה niddah, *niddah*,
she's טמאה *temeah* on Friday,
Friday night she goes to the מקווה *mikvah* and finally here she
can, she's מותר *mutar* to her husband.
Now how about the next day? No, sorry, then you're already bleeding
again.
Okay, how about this week when there's no bleeding?
Well, this bleeding might have been זבה Zavah *zavah* bleeding. If this
was נדה niddah *niddah*, then this was זבה Zavah *zavah*.
זבה Zavah, *zavah* bleed because זבה Zavah *zavah* always comes after נדה
niddah. *niddah* if it's within a certain amount of time.
זבה Zavah *zavah* bleeding requires
seven clean days.
Okay, so how about at the end of this period?
No. That's how come all this time, this is the only time
she can have sex with her husband is the night of the
40th. That's what we said yesterday. Now, there were some other nuances
that we'll go through. Now, how many times does she go to
the מקוה? Mikvah Does she get to go to the מקוה Mikvah
every day, if it's possible? So, there are also nighttimes and daytimes.
And the important thing to remember is that a נדה niddah, goes
to the מקוה Mikvah, at night. She has seven days of full
טומאה, Tumah, it's the night of the end of the seventh day.
She starts bleeding on Sunday, then מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos she goes
to the מקוה, Mikvah, seven days of bleeding. Whether she's bleeding or
not, seven days of טומאה, Tumah she goes the following night. A
זבה Zavah, goes in the day of her seventh clean day. So
if she was bleeding, you know,
I don't know, let's say, she was bleeding Thursday, Friday, שבת, Shabbos
and she started her clean days on Sunday, so שבת Shabbos, in
the day she could go to the מקוה, Mikvah the day of
the seventh, the מקוה Mikvah for the נדה niddah, is the night
following.
So when does this woman go? Maybe I'll use different colors for
nights and days.
I'll use black for night and white
for, anyway.
So,
week number
one, week number one, okay, it's not possible that she's a זבה
Zavah because a זבה Zavah. needs seven clean days and we have
to see the seven clean days, it has to be וספרנו, V'safarnu,
we have to see it. So even if she was clean back
here, it didn't count. Okay, so week number one though, it is
possible that any one of these days is the last day of
her being a יולדת, Yoledes, which is like a נדה, niddah, the
last day of the week or the two weeks of יולדת, Yoledes,
which is like נדה's niddah night following, and therefore since any one
of these days is the last possible day of יולדת, Yoledes, she
would go every single night. So that would be seven nights, okay?
Now, but not again is she a זבה Zavah. because there was
no seven clean days of וספרנו. V'safarnu. Week number two, however, it
could be a, you have, it could be any one of these
days is the last day of being a יולדת, Yoledes, end of
the one week or two weeks from boy or girl, we don't
know whenever that happened, but any one of these days could be
the last, so that's seven nighttimes. But it also could be that
you had seven clean days. The זבה Zavah period could have ended,
you know, the beginning of the counting of the זבה Zavah. could
have been here, seven clean days of זבה, Zavah and then this
is, this daytime you would go. And any of these days could
have been based on the last time she bled, you know, when
she would have started counting her זבה Zavah, period.
Because basically, let me make it clearer, she can only start counting
the זבה zavah, period, as we said, when her יולדת Yoledes period
is over, let her week or two weeks of the boy or
girl are over. So if her week or two weeks of the
girl was over here and acts as a זבה, zavah this would
have been the seventh day and she would go in the daytime.
If however her week or two weeks of the boy or girl
was over here, and this is her זבה zavah. period and she
starts goes to the מקוה Mikvah one day later. So it's all
the way possible that her week or two weeks of the boy
or the girl could get all the way up to here, right?
And then up to the last day would be her seven days
of... Is that clear? And therefore you have another seven days of
going in the daytime for being a זבה. zavah Now, the third
week is the same for the זבה. zavah For your week or
two weeks of the boy, let's say her two weeks of the
girl could have let's say ended here, and then her seven days
of זבה zavah would have ended here, or here, or here, up
to, the two weeks of the girl could have ended here, and
then that would be her last day of the זבה. zavah So
you have the seven daytimes because based on when the two weeks
of the girl ended, the ending of the זבה zavah. period could
have been any day of that week. But you
don't have nighttimes yet, because nighttimes is only for when the period
of the boy or of the יולדת Yoledes of the boy or
girl ends. But that would have definitely ended by the end of
two weeks. Like the טומאה Tumah of a boy or girl is
over after a week or two weeks. So in the third week,
the only thing you're left dealing with is a זבה, zavah, right?
Are you with me? Because the week or two weeks of the
boy or girl, even if it started here, would be over by
here. So by the third week, you only have going seven times
and the גמרא Gemara is going to try to explain how you
could also get seven nights, even though the boy and the girl
טומאה Tumah was over by the end of the second week.
So, that's where we're up to.
Yes?
Is there a reason she'd go to the מקוה Mikvah if they're
not able to have sex?
So nowadays, no. Nowadays, the basic הלכה Halacha that the ראשונים Rishonim
say is either we don't פסקן Pasken טבילה בזמנה מצוה, tvilah bizmanah
mitzvah either we don't פסקן Pasken it at all together, or if
we do פסקן Pasken it, nobody's going to the מקוה mikvah בזמנה
Bizmanah anyway. Because the בזמנה Bizmanah here is, as you see, not
as soon as you're able to have sex, it only says once
in this entire time, it means just when the period is up,
whenever it is, somehow for purposes for טומאה tumah and טהרה Taharah
there's an idea of as soon as you're able you go, even
if it has no yet practical ramifications. nowadays we don't do that
because nowadays women
count seven clean days even if they're most likely a נדה niddah
not a זבה, zavah, so meaning a woman who normally starts bleeding
טבילה בזמנה מצוה tvilah bizmanah mitzvah is really seven days from the
offset of bleeding. A woman is only going to the מקוה mikvah
after seven non-bleeding days. So nobody does בזמנא bizmana nowadays anyway. So
the ראשונים Rishonim say that this even if we פסקן pasken טבילה
בזמנה מצוה tvilah bizmanah mitzvah in theory it's completely moot. However, they
reframe it to say that there is an idea of going as
soon
as to not delay the opportunity for husband and wife to be
together. And it raises interesting questions about the whole issue about going
to the מקוה mikvah, on שבת, Shabbos which is, which is since
it's allowed but it's in a sense somewhat a little problematic because
it raises certain issues we normally don't do on שבת Shabbos? and
so on. So the question is what if somebody delayed going to
the מקוה, mikvah can they still go to the מקוה mikvah on
שבת? Shabbos And those types of questions you have
to use the idea of מצוה mitzvah and is the husband around
or not around, so there's some of that discussion.
But it's a
reframing of what the issue here is.
This in the גמרא Gemara is not about being with the husband,
it's just about doing it at the time, the right time. But
she takes a shower at home. Yeah.
That she takes a shower at home. Yeah.
You mean on שבת Shabbos, how do you handle that? No, I
mean, yeah, yeah,
she does say that, yeah, yeah.
By this argument,
women should be going to the מקוה mikvah on the seventh clean
day, yeah,
during the day
rather than but we don't do that. We don't do that, exactly.
So because that would then undermine the whole idea of requiring seven
clean days if you're going to the מקוה mikvah. earlier and so
on.
If you're going earlier, but you don't go to your husband until
after...
we don't... no, but that would... well, but that would... it would
send a different message. We don't do טבילה בזמנה מצוה tevilah bizmanah
mitzvah. nowadays. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on, so let's
take a look. So again, the bottom of כט עמוד ב. Kaf-Tet
amud bet. And let's,
I'll read what I just sketched up on the board, the first
narrow, the last narrow line. מטבילין אותה תשעים וחמשה טבילות. matbilin otah
tishim vachamishah tvilot. Ninety-five times she goes to the מקוה. mikvah שבוע
קמא מטבילין אותה בלילו. shavuah kamma matbilin otah belilo. The first week
at night. אימא ילדה זכר היא, ima yalda zachar hi, because maybe
that is the end, any day of that could be the end
of her week of a boy, and at the end of her
week of a boy she goes at night. So any day we
don't know when that week started. שבוע שני מטבילין אותה בלילו, shavuah
sheini matbilin otah belilo, and the second week it's at night. אימא
ילדה נקבה היא, ima yalda nekeiva hi, because any night of the
second week could be the end of the two weeks of the
girl, up to the 14th day, right? If she gave, had a
girl the very first day she appeared, then up to the 14th
day could be the last day of טומאת tumat the girl, and
any day earlier could also be whenever she had that miscarriage. She
doesn't know when she had that miscarriage. So that's how you get
the next seven nights. ביממא, bimama, now why does he do during
the day? אימא ילדה זכר וזבה היא, ima yalda zachar vezavah hi,
because maybe she was a זכר zachar and therefore because she's a
זכר zachar the זבה zavah counting would only start, the seven clean
days would
only start after the טומאה tumah period was up. So the טומאה
tumah period might have been up for the first day, and then
it would have been these seven days and she would go at
the beginning of the second week. Or it might have been up
only at the end of the first week, the טומאה tumah period
of זכר, zachar, and then she would only have been able to
go to the מקוה mikvah the last day or any of the
intermediate days based on when the טומאה tumah period was up. So
the second week she goes in the day because that could be
the going to the מקוה mikvah, for being a זבה. zavah,
So now we go on. שבוע שלישי, shavuah shlishi, the third week,
מטבילין אותה ביממא, matbilin otah bimama, same argument. She goes every single
day. אימא ילדה נקבה וזבה היא. ima yalda nekeiva vezavah hi. Maybe
she was a childbirth and a זבה zavah, and it was a
female, so the point is is that the period of טומאה tumah
could have been up any at any time up to the last
day of the second week. And therefore the seven clean days of
a זבה zavah, could have been any day of the third week.
If the טומאה tumah period was up the last day of the
second week, it would have been the last
day of the third week. If the טומאה tumah, period was up
the first day of the second week, then it would have been
the first day of the third week. So every single day of
the third week you get for the cause it might be the
end of the זבה zavah. period. So we have 7, 14, 7.
Now בלילו, belilo, and how about at night? There's no logic for
night, night is not the end of a יולדת yoledet period. So
now we're going to see how בית שמאי Beis Shammai gets to
ninety-five. בית שמאי לטעמיהו, Beis Shammai leta'ameihu, בית שמאי Beis Shammai goes
according to the reasoning דאמרי de'amri טבול יום ארוך בעי טבילה tevul
yom aroch ba'i tvilah that a woman who is a long טבול
יום tevul yom needs טבילה tvilah when it's up, meaning what? A
woman goes to the מקוה, mikvah simple case, a woman gets child,
has a baby, boy or girl, she goes to the מקוה mikvah.
at the end of a week or two weeks. Now she's טהורה,
tehorah. she has one week or two weeks of טומאה, tumah she
goes to the מקוה. mikvah, She's not 100 percent טהורה, tehorah she
is considered she cannot go into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, she's
considered a טבול יום tevul yom like somebody who's gone to the
מקוה, mikvah a שני, sheni,
and you know, if you touch תרומה terumah you're מטמא metamei it,
you can't go into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That only ends
at the end of the 40 or 80 days. But for all
other purposes she's טהורה. tehorah. Okay, so that is considered a טבול
יום, tevul yom, somebody who's gone to the מקוה mikvah but somehow
the טהרה taharah hasn't completed yet, normally it's at night. Here at
66 days later, 30, 33 days later. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says when that period is up, that 66 or 33 days is
up, you have to go to the מקוה mikvah again. Okay, so
it is טבול יום ארוך tevul yom aroch specifically, it is טבול
יום ארוך. tevul yom aroch. Not a guy that goes to the
מקוה mikvah in the day and is finished at night, but for
this long period, there is another need maybe to end it because
it is such a stretched-out period by another going to the מקוה
mikvah at night. Okay, so according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai
basically, what he says is she is going to have to go
every single night through day 80. This is day 80, right? So
it is possible that this was the day that her טומאה tumah
began. This was the day she birthed a girl and she is
all the way until day 80, right, then she becomes totally טהורה.
tehorah, So she definitely goes to the מקוה mikvah? here at night.
But she could have had that girl any day prior up to
80 days before. So every single night could be the last day
of her 80 days. Okay? So according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai,
basically, rather than only go here at night, you go every single
night for 80 days. So if you want to know how many
times you are going according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai. okay, you
have got 80 times for this entire period at night and
then you just add the daytimes, right? So part of the 80
overlaps, right, overlaps this because forget for a second this reason, that
reason. The real reason is any day might
be day 80.
Okay, so
all the nights you are going. Now you just add the daytimes.
There are two weeks of daytimes, right? Here there are two weeks
of
daytimes. That is 94, not 95. But what?
We have to
go to the מקוה?
mikvah I hope they have an annual pass. I hope they have
a subscription.
Maybe you can get like a, what do you call it, like
a MetroCard, like a monthly. Okay,
anyway. All right, so that was just like a bit of a
question.
A question, rabbi. So the first two weeks the woman might be
going for one reason, but she might be going for a different
reason. Sure. So therefore, if you go to מקוה mikvah for any
reason...
Yes, it works. It works.
Yeah. That is an interesting consequence.
Yes, that is correct. Correct. I mean, there is even גמרא Gemara
whatever talking about a woman going to the מקוה mikvah as a
נדה niddah can also count as a גיורת giyores and whatever other
things. Yeah. Yeah.
So is she after each time she goes, is then she טהורה
tehorah to have sex?
No, not sex. Touch things? No, absolutely not because she might be
the last day, but she might be טמא tamei and she might
not and in that case... So then what does she go to
the מקוה mikvah. with no practical consequence? Just to fulfill this idea
that
טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tevilah bizmana mitzvah Okay, so let's take a look.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask the 94 question.
I did the math easy, 80 nights and 14 days. The גמרא
Gemara is going to ask it a little more complicated, but it
is the same point. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מכדי,
michdi, let's take a look, blah blah blah blah blah. ימי טהרה
כמה הוו? Yemei taharah kama havu? How many are the days of
טהרה? taharah? שיתין ושית, Shitin veshis, 66. When 14 days of טומאה
tumah, are gone, 66 days of טהרה. taharah. דל שבוע ג' דטבלינן
להו, Dal shavua gimel detavlinan lehu,
so take away the third week that we made her go to
the מקוה. mikvah פשו
להו שיתין נכי חדא. Pashu lehu shitin nechi chada. So what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is like
this: this
was 14 days of טומאה, tumah, 66 days of טהרה. taharah. Okay,
but we have already now counted the first three weeks. So we
had 66 nights we were going because it might be the last
night according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Subtract seven because we have
already counted those weeks. How many nights from this point on are
you going to go into the מקוה mikvah at night? So 59.
Okay, so that is what it says.
That is 59. So הוו להו פשו להו שיתין נכי חדא, pashu
lehu shitin nechi chada,
60 minus 1, 59. So after three weeks you have 59 nights,
it all must be the last
night. ותלתין וחמש Vesalsin vechamish and 35. Because how much did
we have here?
Right, 14, 28, 35, right?
So 59 plus 35 is how much? 94. Okay, so שיתין נכי
חדא ותלתין וחמש, shitin nechi chada vesalsin vechamish, so 59 plus 35,
תשעין וארבע הוו tishin vearba havu is 94. תשעין וחמש מאי עבידתיהו?
Tishin vechamish mai avidtaihu? How did you get to 95? Okay, so
אמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי, Amar Rabi Yirmeya miDifti, יום שבא לפנינו בין
השמשות, yom sheba lefanenu bein hashmashos, יהבינן ליה טבילה יתירה. yahavinan leh
tevilah yeseirah. Because when she arrived here,
רש"י Rashi simply says she could have said night, so I am
going to say it as if it is night, as if it
is בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. When she arrived at day one, she
did not arrive the daytime. She arrived the night of day one,
the night prior to the הלכה halakhah day, the night prior. So
when she arrived at the night, we said, "Quick, go to מקוה
mikvah right now." Because this might be the last night of the
80 days. So because she came at night of day one, we
got in one other טבילה tevilah there which brought it to 95.
Yes, shouldn't that require another daytime immersion because she started... did not
start out before... because she might have bled right before she arrived.
Yeah, but we are
doing... well the
daytime...
Now how do you get thirty-five? So that's a
pretty radical difference. But בית הלל Beit Hillel אמר סבירא ליה יומא
אריכא לא
בעינן. amar sevira leh yoma aricha lo bainan. So בית הלל Beit
Hillel? doesn't agree with that whole thing about going every single night
as a possible 80th day. So you don't need to go to
the מקווה. Okay, but how do you still stop at
35? Because so let's take a look.
Meaning, according to before we got this idea you go every night,
so we had 7, we had 14, 28. Okay. So how are
you going to get to 35 and stop at 35 according to
בית הלל?
Beit Hillel So let's take a look. ל"ה מאי עבידתייהו? Lamed Heh
mai avidataihu?
How do you get 35? כ"ח כדאמרן. Kaf Chet k'da'amaran.
So 28 we already said. האי שבוע ה'. Hai shavuah hey.
Now the fifth week, מטבילין כל לילה ולילה. matbilin kol lailah v'lailah.
You go every night. אימור סוף נדה היא. eimur sof niddah hee.
Because maybe it is the end of נדה.
niddah What does that mean? So this fifth week here, okay, so
up to here we had 28. Then you bled for seven days.
Now as we pointed out, any one of these days could have
been the beginning of נדה. niddah, This could be the beginning of
נדה, niddah but maybe it's not. Maybe it's one of the days
that she's טהורה. tehorah And each one of these could have been
a beginning of נדה niddah? or could have been a טהור tahor
day. So every night here could be the seventh night from נדה.
niddah, Right? You with me? If this was נדה, niddah. then this
night is the seventh night. If that was נדה, niddah then Monday's
the seventh. If Tuesday was the first day נדה, niddah, then Tuesday
of the next week is the last night. So here you get
another seven nights, one per night, period. Here you get another seven
nights, okay, because every one of those could be the seventh night
from the נדה niddah. the week previous. So perfect. Up to 35.
The question is there should be more. Because after this bleeding you
should, this might be נדה niddah? bleeding, so that should be seven.
It might be זבה zavah. bleeding, so that should even give you
some daytime, right? So every טהור tahor week should have at least
seven nights and a few days based on the possibility of נדה
niddah. and זבה. zavah. Okay, actually not if you need seven clean
days. Yes, okay. But every next week should have seven, seven more
nights. So it shouldn't end at 35. It should be in the
whatever, it should be like 60 or something.
So let's take a look.
So I'll tell you the answer because the גמרא Gemara is not
going to give you the answer right away. The answer the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is that בית הלל Beit Hillel stops
counting after she gets to see her husband. So בית הלל Beit
Hillel says 35 is not meaning 35 for the entire period like
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. He only wants 35 up until she can
see her husband. But actually if you added the other weeks, there
would be 7, 14, 21, it would actually be 56.
Okay. So it's not as radical as the בית הלל Beit Hillel
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai So that's that. Now the גמרא Gemara says,
don't worry, we're coming in for a landing. So the גמרא Gemara
says like
this. Okay. י"ג שבועין למה לי? Yud Gimmel shavuon lamma lee? בתמנאו
פלגא סלקי. B'tamneu palga salki.
We are only, this is the only question as the doubt for
this other status goes up to day 80. After day 80 then
we can, then there's no doubt left.
Any issue of יולדת yoledet is over.
80 days is the maximum of the doubt. So if we only
wanted to discuss, so after that this whole case stops being so
interesting. So why did we say 13? We could have said three
weeks plus ten, which gives us 13. If you said three weeks
plus eight and a half, wait, three weeks, eight and a half,
eleven and a half, gets you to day 80. So why did
it give the scenario of 13 weeks if it stops being interesting
after 11 and a half?
So that's the question. So it says, איידי דתני פלגא דשבוע מסיק
ליה. Aidi d'tani palga d'shavuah masik leh.
So since it would have gotten you to 8 and a half,
11 and a half rather, it's 8 plus 3. So you don't
want to end in a half. So you give a scenario of
a full week. So it gets you up to 12. איידי דתני
שבוע טמא. Aidi d'tani shavuah tamei. And since month 12 is with
blood, so and we've been talking about a pair of bleeding and
not bleeding, תני נמי שבוע טהור. tani nami shavuah tahor. So we
also said the 13th week was טהור. tahor. But really the real
point is that this case stops being interesting after day 80. Okay.
Now moving on. ואיכא טבילות זבה דלפני תשמיש. V'ika tvilot zavah d'lifnei
tashmish. הויא טבילת זבה. Hava tvilat zavah. So it says דלפני תשמיש
קחשיב דאחר תשמיש לא קחשיב. D'lifnei tashmish kachashiv d'achar tashmish lo kachashiv.
So it's basically saying the question is now answered, which
is why does בית הלל Beit Hillel stop counting after this? Now
I said if you count the נדה niddah days, if he considers
this to be a נדה, niddah, then he'd be going every night
there. But even if you consider this to be a זבה, zavah.
this was נדה niddah. and this was זבה, zavah so you still
have seven clean days and at least you'd go once at the
end of the week. So it's the same question which is why
does בית הלל stop counting after
this?
דלמא תשמיש כחשיב דלאחר תשמיש לא כחשיב. Dilma tashmish kachashiv delachar tashmish
lo kachashiv. ולבית שמאי דכחשיב דלאחר תשמיש, UleBeis Shammai dekachashiv delachar tashmish,
going to בית שמאי Beis Shammai, they’re counting the entire
eighty-day period. ניחשב נמי טבילת זבה? Nichshov nami tvilas zavah?
So how about the זבה zavah טבילה? tvila?
Meaning according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we stopped counting, we should
have stopped counting. For בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, we had every single
night until day eighty. But there are some day טבילות tvilas as
well, right? Because if this is a זבה, zavah then she goes
the day here. And if this is a זבה, zavah. then she
goes the day here. And if this is a זבה, zavah. she
goes the day here. So what, according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai
we forgot some? Could it get up to ninety-eight maybe or
something?
Okay, so it says,
so it says
דלידה קאמרי בזובה לא קאמרי. Delayda kaamri bizviva lo kaamri. No, we’re
not interested in going to the מקוה mikvah for זבה. zavah, We’re
only interested in going to the מקוה mikvah for יולדת. yoledes. Gemara
says, no, you can’t say that. ואיכא יולדת בזוב. Ve’ika yoledes b’zove.
We just counted here going to the מקוה mikvah for זבה. zavah.
The seven days here was going to the מקוה mikvah, for זבה.
zavah So we are counting טבילה tvila for זבה. zavah, So yeah,
but the Gemara’s answer is going to be, as the phrase indicates,
יולדת בזוב. yoledes b’zove. That’s going for a זבה zavah when your
לידה layda came with your זובה zova and it all came together.
That’s like wrapping up the לידה-זובה. But a new זבה zavah type
of thing, that we’re not counting, which makes sense because all of
the טבילה tvila that בית שמאי is counting is based on the
eighty days. They’re counting all about יולדת. yoledes. Eighty days of טבילה
tvila because of יולדת, yoledes, eighty nights I should say. And all
of these are also wrapping up the לידה layda and the maybe
זבה zavah. that came with it. So the basic point is I’m
not going to count things that are
new reasons to go to the מקוה, mikvah I’m just counting wrapping
up the old stuff. Let’s just read that answer one minute. ואיכא
יולדת בזוב. Ve’ika yoledes b’zove. You can’t say you’re not counting זבה.
zavah We have the first three weeks which you were going to
the מקוה mikvah because of, because you were a זבה. zavah. יולדת
בזוב כחשיב זיבה גרידתא לא כחשיב. Yoledes b’zove kachashiv ziva geridaisa lo
kachashiv. It’s counting giving birth as being a when being a זבה,
zavah because that’s all about wrapping up the childbirth. But not talking
about new just being a זבה. zavah, So they have eighty nights
because every night might be the last night, and they have twenty-one
in the, what do they have,
fourteen in the beginning in the daytime because the childbirth might have
happened concomitant with the זיבה. ziva. So all the טבילות tvilas of
wrapping it up we’re going to count and that will be ninety-five,
but new reasons to go to the מקוה mikvah we’re not going
to count.
My question is, during this time she’s bled one, two, three, four,
five times, right? So then
why don’t we say that after three times of bleeding and that’s
already her new cycle and her new cycle is just like two
weeks or something? Are we saying that there
is
no thing as נדה?
niddah. No, I’ll give you two short answers. One is there’s a
question whether bleeding בימי זיבתה bimei zivasah on when it is קובע
וסת בתוך ימי זיבתה. kovea vest besoch yemei zivasah. So it could
be that bleeding during this period of זבה zavah, period can't be
קובע וסת. kovea vest. Number two, even if it’s קובע וסת, kovea
vest, the הלכה halacha is that even if a woman bleeds on
her cycle, it doesn’t make her a not a זבה, zavah it
doesn’t make her a נדה, niddah if it’s within a certain amount
of days after the last bleeding. Regardless of cycle, cycle doesn’t redefine
you as a נדה. niddah, Regardless of the established cycle, if it’s
within between day eight and day nineteen of the, day eight and
day eighteen of the previous bleeding, the woman’s a זבה zavah regardless
of when her cycle is. Okay, so let’s take a look. Gemara
continues.
Okay, so it says like this. שבעה קמאי דחזיה לכולהו ליטבלהו ביממי?
Shiva kamai dechazya lekulhu litvileyhu biymama? דילמא כל יומא ויומא שחמי ליה
ספורים דידה? Dilma kol yoma veyoma chamia lei sefurim didah?
So I’ve already given you the answer, but the Gemara says
why not here go to the מקוה mikvah in the day, every
single day, because maybe she was a זבה zavah and she had
her seven clean days, wasn’t mentioned. So maybe the last seven clean
days before she came to us she wasn’t bleeding were seven clean
days and any one of these days could be the last after
seven clean days of being a זבה. zavah So let her go
every morning, you know, every morning here. Maybe there were seven clean
days that preceded or five days that preceded plus two or four
days plus three. Why do we only start counting the seven clean
days of a זבה zavah. when she appears? Maybe they began earlier?
That’s the Gemara’s question. And it says and this is actually one
of the significant הלכות halachos that emerge from this. So the Gemara
says דילמא כל יומא ויומא שחמי ליה ספורים דידה, Dilma kol yoma
veyoma chamia lei sefurim didah, maybe any day of the first week
was the end of the seven clean days? So הא מני רבי
עקיבא היא, Ha manni Rabbi Akiva hi, דאמר בעינן ספורים לפנינו. De’amar
beinan sefurim lefanenu. It’s רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that says, we’ll see that later, that if she was טהור tahor
and she was completely unaware of it, if she didn’t bleed and
unaware of it, it doesn’t count towards her clean days of a
זבה. zavah. She has to be aware that she is not bleeding
for it to count for her טהור tahor days. Okay. So the
Gemara says, or maybe aware to physically count it, well whatever, we’ll
see that later. So the Gemara says סוף שבוע קמא לטבלה. Sof
shavua kama litvile. So how about the end of week one? He
says fine.
So she can only start counting טבילה. tvila. But remember a זבה
zavah. can go to the מקוה mikvah in the Morning of the
tenth day. So why can't she count one extra טבילה tvila here?
These were the seven clean days of a זבה, zavah. the morning
of שבת, Shabbos let's say it started on Sunday let her go.
Okay, so why not the morning of day of week one?
So the גמרא Gemara says חד בשבועא לא קמיירי. chada bashavua lo
kama'irei.
We're not just going to count one day, a solitary day in
an entire week. You're right, really she should, and that'll get us
up to 96 or 36 or whatever but we're not counting singleton
days. Okay,
whatever. Let's keep moving. I think it's true, I think we don't
have any singleton days here, but anyway. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara said, okay,
יומא קמא דאתיא קמה לטבלה. yoma kama datia kama litvilah. So דילמא
שומרת יום כנגד יום היא. dilma shomeret yom kineged yom hi.
So the גמרא Gemara says how about, okay, but not a singleton
day since she waits close to ten days. You've got this
Saturday day, שבת Shabbos day that she might be a זבה, zavah.
but if she appeared for us on Sunday, let her go Sunday
day. Why Sunday day? Because and then it'll be two times in
the week. Why Sunday day? Because the day before she came to
us Saturday, she might have bled once. She might have been a
זבה קטנה, zava ktana, a woman who bleeds once during her non-cycle
period, once or twice, and needs only one clean day, not seven
clean days. So if she bled the day before she came, then
Sunday the first day she appears is her clean day and let
her go Sunday in the morning. So she should go שבת in
the morning because it could be the end of the seven clean
days, and she should go Sunday in the morning when she appeared,
because maybe she was a זבה קטנה zava ktana and only required
one clean day. And then you have two times in the week
that she's going.
So the גמרא Gemara says, דילמא שומרת יום כנגד יום היא, dilma
shomeret yom kineged yom hi,
maybe she's a woman who watches one day opposite one day, meaning
she bleeds for one day as a זבה zavah so she watches
only needs one clean day. The גמרא Gemara says בזבה גדולה קמיירי
בזבה קטנה לא קמיירי. bezava gdola kamairei bezava ktana lo kamairei. All
right, we're talking about the big categories, the weeks, we're talking about
a זבה גדולה, zava gdola, we're not worried about the זבה קטנה.
zava ktana. So if you added everything up, probably get you about
100. Okay, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara wraps the whole thing up,
and that was a lot of fun. שמע מינה תלת, shmina tlat,
we learn from all this three things. שמע מינה רבי עקיבא היא
דאמר בעינן ספורים בפנינו, shmina Rabi Akiva hi d'amar bivinan sfarim bifaneinu,
meaning by our analysis I guess we figured out three things. Number
one, that it's assuming רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, that if you have
clean days, non-bleeding days, they can't count if you're not aware that
they're clean. Okay, that's בפנינו. bifaneinu. That could have very relevant הלכות
halachot nowadays, right, for a woman who you know wasn't aware that
she was during her שבעה נקיים, shiva nekiim, but she has maybe
some evidence that she wasn't bleeding or something like that. Anyway, exactly
what are the parameters of בפנינו bifaneinu we'll discuss, but that is
a very important הלכה. halacha. So you need to be—it's not enough
that you didn't bleed, there needs to be some sense that it's
happening בפנינו, bifaneinu, some awareness of it. ושמע מינה רבי שמעון היא
דאמר אבל אמרו חכמים אסור לעשות כן שמא תבוא לידי ספק. ushmina
Rabi Shimon hi d'amar aval amru chachamim asur laasot ken shema tavo
lidei safek.
It's also learned that we are assuming here רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon,
that a woman cannot go to the מקוה mikvah on the seventh
day of being a זבה zavah. and have sex that day, because
we're
concerned—she can have sex that night but not that day, because we're
concerned that if she'll have sex and bleed later then it will
retroactively have defined that day as a טמא tamei day and the
מקוה mikvah won't have counted. Remember we discussed that yesterday. So since
we had a question like why here does she have to only
do it one night, how about there's an earlier time she could
go to the מקוה mikvah in the day and have sex that
day before she bleeds, and it says no no no, it's רבי
שמעון Rabi Shimon who says that when a זבה zavah goes to
the מקוה mikvah the day of the seventh before the day is
out, she's not allowed to have sex later that day because if
she bleeds later it'll undermine the entire day.
Yes, women who used to go—not have sex during the day.
Oh, that's a good question. Yeah, but that is, that is, that
is—there are more—you're good. There are more exceptions to that rule, a
dark house. There are exceptions to that rule, for example, a dark
house, other types of things, you know, talking about how much light
is defined.
Very light, very light, yeah, like it has to be very dark.
All right, but that's but one is the הלכה halacha in sort
of like דרך ארץ, derech eretz, the other is הלכה halacha in
הלכות נדה. hilchot niddah. So there's sort of like different weight to
that, okay? The concern that you actually wind up having sex when
the
woman—when she—you know,
when it retroactively turned out that she was a זבה zavah. or
a נדה niddah is a much bigger, weightier halachic concern than those
other things, but you're correct that there are exceptions to the cases
of sex during the day. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says תליתי. tlitai. So the גמרא Gemara says that's number
two, and number three—remember we always learn three things, never two, never
four, it's always three. I'm serious, okay? That's what they tell you
in speech classes, they say, you know, always say there are three
lessons we can—there's three points I want to make, because everybody remembers
three. שמא תבוא לידי ספק, shema tavo lidei safek,
ושמע מינה טבילה בזמנה מצווה. ushmina tvila bizmanah mitzvah. And what we
hear is from all of these Hillel/Shammai-style assumptions that at least when
we're still in that world of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah and when
it's still—we still—it's possible to go during the right time, we would
say that you go when it's the right time regardless of if
it has any practical benefit. There's a מצווה mitzvah to go at
the right time. Now, the end of the ברייתא is רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר דיה לטבילה באחרונה. Rabi Yose b'Rabi Yehuda omer daya
l'tvila baacharonah. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabi Yose b'Rabi Yehuda says forget
this 95, 35, just go to the מקוה mikvah once and be
done with it. When you're definitely טהור tahor go to the מקווה
at the right before night 35 go to the מקווה have sex
with the husband and then if you have to wait another whatever
till the end of day 80 go once more then and be
done with it. Go when it's relevant. Don't go every single night.
So he says we don't say טבילה בזמנה tevilah bizmana מצוה that
there's a point of going to the מקווה just when it's the
right night. There's a point of going when you're able to become
טהור tahor and not just for the sake of it being the
right time. So that was a lovely digression, very complicated, but you
know, a little fun. Anyway, in sort of demonstrating definitely certain הלכות
halachot about when you go to the מקווה and about טבילה בזמנה
and all these various other considerations. So now we go on. That
was all brought in to make some point about whether we're normally
concerned about a woman when she gives, when she miscarries, and we
don't know what she miscarried, do we assume that it was a,
considered a halachic fetus or not. Now we finally turn to this
משנה, mishna, bottom of ל' עמוד א', lamed amud aleph, which is,
talks about what we've always been assuming, which is how much is
the fetus developed to be considered viable? That only at a certain
point, once it's sort of developed, is it really considered a fetus,
and a miscarriage is considered a birth. Prior to that point of
development, it's not considered a miscarriage, and that also has implications for
parameters about abortion and other types of issues about at what stage
is it really considered a fetus. So let's take a look. Here's
what the משנה mishna says. המפלת ליום ארבעים, hamapelet l'yom arbaim, if
a woman miscarries on day 40 of conception, from conception,
אין חוששת לולד, ein chosheshet l'valad, she's not, it's not, yeah right,
it's just not developed enough, it does not have a status of
a fetus. ליום ארבעים ואחד, l'yom arbaim v'echad, day 41, then it
has a status of a fetus, and if she doesn't know what
it is, תשב לזכר ולנקבה ולנדה. teshev l'zachar u'linekeva u'leniddah. She has
to be concerned it's a male or it's a female, which if
it's a male it's a week of טומאה, tumah, if it's a
female it's two weeks, and maybe it's a נדה, niddah meaning maybe
it was not viable, or was not, you know, maybe it wasn't
even a fetus if she assuming she couldn't inspect it and see
that it was a fetus, and therefore if it wouldn't count as
a fetus altogether, then she has no days of טהרה. tahara. So
she has two weeks of טומאה, tumah. might have been a female,
no days of טהרה tahara because it might not have been a
fetus. But the point is it only becomes an issue starting on
day 41. Now day 41 since when? How do you know when
conception? So רש"י Rashi says you count from the מקווה night, that's
when you're assuming they've had sex and so on. But obviously there's
other ways to determine, right, you know, if a woman's pregnant she
goes to the doctor, right, I mean, I know now maybe there's
other ways of testing it, I'm sure there are, but I know,
you know, at least in the olden days I know the doctor
said, "So when do you think you became pregnant?" Right, so normally
people have a good idea when the night of conception was. So
anyway, okay, so that's just, so anyway day 41 is when it's
considered developed enough that it would have that status and therefore she
has to be, you know, have the appropriate טומאה.
tumah, But you don't know exactly.
You don't know exactly. Right. I know. So that raises questions if
you cannot exactly know. I mean that you could, I guess you
can't because even if they had sex one night and not another
night, right, it could have, the egg could have been inseminated two
or three nights, two or three days later. Right. That's a good
point. Yeah. So I guess you would have to, you know, you'd
just have to treat it like any ספק. safek. It seems like
the גמרא Gemara though, the משנה mishna makes it sound like you
can be precise.
It seems like they think that you will be, that a woman
will become pregnant on the night that she...
Yeah, they did assume that, but on the other hand the גמרא
Gemara also says other places that it assumes that semen remains potent
for three days, or at least a day and a half depending
on different positions.
And presumably, I'd have to check, that גמרא's Gemara not explicit whether
it means that it's potent to the point that it could create,
it could impregnate. That's more for the הלכות halachot of שכבת זרע
shichvat zera and טומאת שכבת זרע. tumat shichvat zera. But that's certainly
the assumption I've always had. The גמרא Gemara has other cases where...
Yeah, I mean, you're right. I think the גמרא Gemara
implicitly at least knows that it doesn't have to, that the semen
can wait in the body before creating, before impregnating.
So it does raise that question. But at less than six weeks
I'm not sure
that you would know the gender of the fetus.
Well, that's why it's always assuming that you don't. You therefore say...
No, but even today you could with a DNA test.
Oh, yeah, but even in 40 days or a few more days...
Right.
So that's why it's taking it for granted that you don't know
the gender. That's why I'd say you have to treat it as
both male and female. That might be 40 days. That might be.
That's why earlier משניות mishnayot said, the previous משנה mishna yesterday said
exactly that. You have a miscarriage and you can't tell if it's
a boy or a girl. So the משנה mishna assumes regularly that
it won't be able to tell if it's a boy or a
girl.
That's why it says תשב לזכר
ולנקבה
ולנדה.
teshev
l'zachar u'linekeva u'leniddah.
Right. That's the whole point. But, but right, it's not assuming that
if it was 60 days later you could. That previous משנה mishna
assumed many cases of miscarriage you cannot. Right, that was assumed in
the previous משנה. mishna. Okay, now רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer,
famous position of רבי ישמעאל,
אומר
Rabbi Yishmael
omer, ליום ארבעים ואחד, day 41, if she miscarries, תשב לזכר ולנדה.
teshev l'zachar u'leniddah. You have to be concerned it might be a
boy and therefore it's a week of טומאה, tumah, or maybe it's
not even a fetus at all, or not,
not properly developing or whatever, and therefore not טמא tamei at all,
excuse me, no days of. tahara. So a week of טומאה, tumah,
no days of טהרה, tahara, but you don't have to be concerned
it's a girl. However,
if it's יום—well yom you'll see—if it's יום פ״א, Yom Peh Alef,
day 81, תשב לזכר ולנקבה לנדה. teishev le-zachar u-le-nekeiva le-niddah. Then you
have to be concerned maybe boy, maybe girl, maybe a נדה. niddah
Now, why? She tells you: שזכר נגמר למ״א, she-zachar nigmar le-mem alef,
because a male child will gets to a stage of a certain
degree of development at day 41. But הנקבה לפ״א, ha-nekeiva le-peh alef,
but a female only gets developed at day 81 to the same
stage of development. So I guess they mature, they get puberty earlier,
but the fetal development comes later according to him. Why? Where do
you think... where do you think he's getting this number of 80
for a girl for? Because there's 80 days until the mother is
טהורה, right? I mean there's two weeks of טומאה, tumah 66 days
of טהרה, tahara, a period of 80 days for the mother. And
he assumes that that period of 40 days for the birth of
a boy and 80 days for the birth of a girl for
the טומאה טהרה tumah tahara of the mother
reflects the stages of development of the fetus. Okay. So וחכמים אומרים,
ve-chachamim omrim, וחכמים chachamim say, אחד ביאת הזכר ואחד ביאת הנקבה זה
וזה למ״א. echad biyat ha-zachar ve-echad biyat ha-nekeiva zeh ve-zeh le-mem alef.
No, male or female is only by 41 days the fetus is
developed, it's considered to be a viable—yes. And never so,
let's take a look. We are up to about to—I think probably
the most radical contrast of an עמוד א׳ amud alef and an
עמוד ב׳. amud bet. The עמוד א׳ amud alef was all this
difficult computation, the עמוד ב׳ amud bet is a lot of אגדתא.
aggadata. So let's take a look. למה הוזכר זכר? Lama huzkar zachar?
We're getting into fun discussions about fetal development. למה הוזכר זכר? Lama
huzkar zachar? Now, why? First we have a הלכה halachic point to
pay attention to. What meaning does it have to say it might
be a boy, it might be a girl, might be—might be just
a נדה? niddah Right. If you say נקבה, nekeiva, it gives you
your two weeks. If you want to say you don't get טהרה
tahara days, say it might be a נדה. niddah A boy doesn't
add טומאה tumah days because it's a week rather than two and
it has less טהרה tahara days. But saying נדה niddah means no
טהרה tahara days. So what's added by saying it might be a
boy? So: אי לימי טומאה הכתני נקבה, i le-yemei tumah hakateni nekeiva,
if to say that you're טמא, tameh, we have two weeks of
טומאה tumah for the girl. אי לימי טהרה, i le-yemei tahara, if
to say you don't have the full 80 days of טהרה tahara
for the girl, הכתני נדה, hakateni niddah, but we said she might
not be a יולדת yoledes at all and has no טהרה tahara
days. So here's the
נפקא מינה: nafka mina: שתראה ליום ל״ד ותחזור ותראה יום מ״א. she-tira
le-yom lamed daled ve-chachra ve-tira yom mem alef. That—let's say she bled
on day 34 and then bleeds again on day—I'm sorry, מ״א, mem
alef, on 41, תהא מקולקלת עד מ״ח. tehei mekulkela ad mem chet.
So she doesn't know her status till day 48. What does this
show?
Oh,
let's arrange this gorgeous picture here. Yes. Alright. Anyway, enough of that.
So this is much more simple, okay? Here she is, she had
her miscarriage, she doesn't know what her status is, okay? So, here's
day 40. Okay. What does it say? She gave birth when?
When did she say?
שתראה יום ל״ד.
she-tira
yom sheloshim ve-arba. 34. Okay. So she bleeds on day 34. Okay.
And then again on day 41. Now what's her status? If we
knew that it was a... if it was a boy, what would
her status be? This does not make her נדה, niddah. it's in
her טהרה tahara days. This makes her נדה. niddah. She's a נדה.
If however it's not a boy, if it's a girl, what's her
status? She's טהורה לגמרי. tehorah le-gamrei. If it's not a boy or
a girl, what's her status? Here she's a נדה and here she's
a זבה. zavah A second
bleeding, right,
after—between days 8 and 18 is a זבה. zavah, So therefore because
of the possibility... if it was just יולדת yoledes versus נדה, she
would either be טהורה or a זבה. zavah.
It's not day 18, it's day 7. 34 to 41.
No, 34 to 35, 36...
Oh, you're counting 34.
So anyway, so if she was a... so if she was just
a maybe a נדה and maybe a נקבה, nekeiva, it would either
be טהורה
or it would be a זבה. zava, Because it's also might be
a boy, you also have to throw in the possibility that she
is a נדה and not a זבה.
zava, But
only if she bleeds those two times. Okay. Now, why does it
matter? Because, right, why does it matter? Because even though for זבה
zava she's טמא tameh and for a נדה she's טמא, tameh, she's
even more טמא tameh for a זבה. But as we've been saying,
you've got to know when your last bleeding made you a נדה
or זבה so you know whether your next bleeding, right, makes you
a נדה or זבה. The status of the blood and whether it
makes you נדה or זבה depends on what your status was prior.
So therefore in that case, תהא מקולקלת עד מ״ח. tehei mekulkela ad
mem chet. She's mixed up, she is until day 48. I'm not
going to figure it out for you, but you can try to
figure it out yourself. Basically, by day 48, she can get seven
clean days, go to the מקוה and then start the cycle afresh.
But because of this possibility, she doesn't know at all what her
status is because—because she might not just maybe be a זבה, she
also maybe might be a נדה. וכן לענין נקבה, ve-chein le-inyan nekeiva,
and a similar issue would come up for a female. שתראה יום
ע״ד ותחזור ותראה יום פ״א. she-tira yom ayin daled ve-chachra ve-tira yom
peh alef. If she saw day 74 and day 81, so also
you don't know. Maybe it wasn't a girl, and therefore both of
those were טמא tameh and therefore she's a זבה. Maybe it was
a girl, and therefore the first one was טהור tahor and the
second is טמא tameh and she's a נדה. case she doesn't know
נידה niddah or זבה, תמתין tamtein כולה kullah עד יום פ"ח ad
Yom Pe Chet and then she can have seven clean days and
go to the מקווה and start it all again. Okay, so if
a woman basically doesn't know whether she's a נידה niddah or a
זבה, then she's not going to know how to treat the next
bleeding, whether the next bleeding will make her a נידה niddah or
זבה will be depending on what the previous one was, and therefore
that's why גמרא said it might be a boy makes a difference.
Alright, let's move on. רבי ישמעאל אומר יום ארבעים ואחד תשב לזכר
ולנידה. Rabbi Yishmael omer Yom Arbaim ve-Echad teshev le-Zachar u-le-Niddah. Day 41,
boy, she doesn't have to worry about a girl. תניא, Tanya, תני
בריתא, tni braisa, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael, אומר, טימא וטיהר בזכר וטימא
וטיהר בנקבה. tamei ve-tiher be-zachar ve-tamei ve-tiher be-nekeiva. The תורה Torah gives
you days of טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah for a boy and
טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah for a girl. מה כשטימא וטיהר בזכר
יצירתו כיוצא בו, Ma ke-she-tamei ve-tiher be-zachar yetzirato ke-yotzei vo, the same
way when it gives you the טומאה tumah and טהרה taharah days
of a boy, his forming of the fetus is equal to the
days of טומאה tumah and טהרה, taharah, 40 days of formation, 40
days of טומאה tumah and טהרה. taharah. אף כשטימא וטיהר בנקבה, Af
ke-she-tamei ve-tiher be-nekeiva, similarly when it gave you days of טומאה tumah
and טהרה taharah by a girl, 80 days, 14 and 66, so
יצירתה כיוצא בה, yetziratah ke-yotzei bah, her formation as a fetus equals
those days. So if the mother has the status for 80 days,
the girl is not considered developed until day 80. אמרו לו, Amru
lo, they said back to him, אין למידין יצירה מטומאה. ein le-meidin
yetzirah mi-tumah. No, who says they're linked?
It's a nice little דרשה, drasha, but who tells you that the
days of טומאה tumah have anything to do with the days of
fetal formation? אמרו לו לרבי ישמעאל, Amru lo le-Rabbi Yishmael, they said
to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, now it gets
interesting, מעשה בקליאופטרה מלכת אלכסנדרוס, maaseh bi-Cleopatra malkas Alexandros, so there's a
story of קליאופטרה, Cleopatra, the queen of
אלכסנדרוס. Alexandros. Now does
who was קליאופטרה Cleopatra married to? Was she Mark Antony?
No, she
was married to her brother.
Okay, she had lovers. Okay, fine. Alright, anyway. Alright, but who was
קליאופטרה? Cleopatra?
I understand, I understand.
Alright, anyway. Okay, but anyway, forget who she's married to. She was
the queen of Alexandria, שנתחייבו שפחותיה הריגה, she-nis-chayvu shifchoseha harigah, that her
maidservants
were decreed for death, they had done some crime למלכות, le-malchus, death
to the kingdom. ובדקן, U-badkan, some people say that this story is
a development of the idea that when קליאופטרה Cleopatra was planning to
kill herself, she tried different ways of committing suicide on her maidservants
to see which was the most painless and effective. Anyway, so there
was obviously stories about her killing her maidservants. Anyway, so her many
Queen קליאופטרה. Cleopatra.
That's also true. Okay, so anyway, when they had to be put
to death, the
maidservants, ובדקן, u-badkan, so basically the backstory here is, which is implicit,
that רש״י Rashi tells out, she had them get pregnant and then
she was going to kill them and do a little dissection and
see what the state of fetal development was. So she checked them,
ומצאן זה
וזה לאחד וארבעים, u-matzan zeh ve-zeh le-achad ve-arbaim, and when she basically
did an autopsy and did the dissection, she saw that some had
boys and some had girls and it was day 41 and they
were both equally developed.
How were you really able to tell, you know, even then?
Yeah, I know. אמר להן, Amar lahen, so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
said back to the חכמים, chachamim, אני מביא לכם ראיה מן התורה,
ani meivi lachem rayah min ha-Torah, look, I'm quoting פסוקים, psukim, you
might agree or disagree, but I'm quoting פסוקים. psukim. ואתם מביאים לי
ראיה מן השוטים? Ve-atem meivim li rayah min ha-shoteim? You're bringing me
a proof from fools?
So you're giving me empirical evidence.
Exactly, exactly. Exactly.
So, so now let's take a look. מה ראיה מן התורה? Ma
rayah min ha-Torah? What's the proof from the תורה? Torah? אילימא טימא
וטיהר בזכר וטימא וטיהר בנקבה, Ileima tamei ve-tiher be-zachar ve-tamei ve-tiher be-nekeiva,
if it's the proof you said that look, 40 days of טומאה
tumah and טהרה, taharah, 80 days of טומאה tumah. and טהרה, taharah,
that should indicate days of
development, הא קאמרי ליה אין דנין יצירה מטומאה. ha ka-amreilei ein danyin
yetzirah mi-tumah. So you can't learn development from טומאה. To no, he
has another פסוק. pasuk. אמר קרא תלד, Amar kra teileid, the פסוק
pasuk says ואם נקבה תלד, ve-im nekeiva teileid, it emphasizes by the
girl again the verb of giving birth. הוסיף לה הכתוב לידה אחרת,
Hosif lah ha-kasuv leidah acheres, which somehow indicates that there's a, I
don't know exactly, another birth or somehow meaning a more extended period
of the process, that's how he learns out from the extra verb
of תלד teileid that the period for the girl is more extended.
Alright, I understand. בנקבה, Be-nekeiva, by a girl. Anyway, he does regardless
whether they agreed or disagreed, at least he was bringing proof from
פסוקים. psukim. So ומה ראיה מן השוטים? u-ma rayah min ha-shoteim? Why
does he call this evidence from
fools? I mean it was as being said empirical evidence. No, it's
not good empirical evidence. אימא נקבה קדים ועיבר ארבעים יומין קמי זכר.
Eima nekeiva kadam ve-ubar arbaim yomin kamei zachar. Yes, maybe the girl,
the baby girl fetus, again how do they know, I don't know,
which is also not being asked, but maybe the baby girl fetus
was fully developed day 40 after she began her test, but maybe
the maidservant had been pregnant for 40 days when she was beginning
her test. So how do you know? You weren't dealing with necessarily
like, you know, laboratory conditions. So it could be that the girl
had been developed 80 days, maybe the maidservant had already been pregnant.
All right, so that wasn't a good proof. Now, ורבנן, ve-rabbanan, and
the rabbis, how did they, why did they argue it was a
good proof? סמא דנישקא Sama de-nishka Anyway, some anything, something that basically
would. Ah, maybe. Maybe she did. Right. All right. It's an assertion.
I don't know if they're claiming that they actually knew. Right. Anyway,
whatever. She made her drink, she made them drink something that would
have caused miscarriage. So she did start from a clean slate. Before
she started her experiment, she made them drink something that would have
caused any fetus to have been discharged. So Rabbi Ishmael, what would
Rabbi Ishmael say back? איכא גופא דלא מקבלא סמא, Ika gufa dela
mikabla sama, doesn't work on all people. There's some fetuses it doesn't
work on, so again it was not a pure experiment. אמר להם
רבי ישמעאל, Amar lahem Rabbi Yishmael, now, Rabbi Ishmael said, now there's
another version that the evidence from Cleopatra was the opposite. Rabbi Ishmael
said to them, מעשה בקליאופטרה מלכת
יוונית, Maaseh bi'Cleopatra malkat Yevanit, interesting, first
one they called Alexander, here it's calling Greek. Anyway, story with Cleopatra
and what? She was Greek. Okay. The Greek queen, שנתחייבו שפחותיה הריגה,
Shenitchayvu shefachoteha hariga, that her maidservants had to be put to death
למלכות Lemalchut to the government, ובדקן ומצא U'vadkan u'matza and she checked
them and she opened them up, she found, זכר לארבעים ואחד ונקבה
לשמונים ואחד. Zachar le'arbaim ve'echad u'nekeiva le'shmonim ve'echad.
She found that there was a girl that was 81 days developed
and a boy that was 40 days developed, I don't know exactly
how she knew, and she saw that they were the same stage
of development. So אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him,
אין מביאין ראיה מן השוטים. Ein mevi'in ra'aya min hashotim. Don't bring
proof from fools. Why is it a proof from fools? מאי טעמא,
Mai ta'ama, הדא נקבה איצטרא ארבעים יומין והדר איעבר. Hada nekeiva itztara
arbaim yomin vehadar i'ever.
Who says that the woman that you checked after 81, the maidservant
that you killed after 81 days and then found this girl that
was developed, maybe she didn't have sex on the first day you
tried to put her together with this man. Maybe she had sex,
you know, 40 days later. Maybe this fetus was 40 days developed,
not 80 days developed. So he says, Rabbi Ishmael, לשומר מסרינום. Leshomer
mesaranum. No, they put the women in, they put a guard on
top of the, you know, to ensure over the women to make
sure that after they had sex on the day that they were
doing the experiment, that they didn't have sex anymore until they executed
them. רבנן, Rabbanan, what would the Rabbis say back? אין אפוטרופוס לעריות,
Ein apotropus l'arayot, which is a very important halakhic principle actually. There
is no such thing as chaperones when it comes to sex. Okay.
So, I'm sorry, you might have had somebody try to protect her,
but you cannot prove that they did not find a way to
have sex afterwards and you don't know whether this fetus was developed
80 days or 40 days. And why
not? How could it be? He gives an easy example. אימור שומר
גופו בא עליה. Eimor shomer gufo ba aleha. Maybe the guard had
sex with her, you know, so who knows, right? So anyway, so
okay, you say it was 80 days after you did your experiment
and had them sleep with a guy, but maybe it was actually
she got pregnant 40 days later and you can't prove otherwise. So
the Gemara says, ודילמא אי קרו להא נקבה בארבעים וחד הויא משתכחא
כזכר. Vedilma i karu l'ha nekeiva b'arbaim ve'chad hava mishtakcha k'zachar. So
the Gemara says one minute, how do you know that this fetus
at 80 days developed, you know, how do you know that at
40 days it wasn't also equally developed? Even if you say you're
right. Okay, it was 80 days developed, we looked at it and
it was developed. But maybe it was the same stage of development
40 days ago. So how do you know not? So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, בסימניהון שוין. Besimaneihon shavin. No, they were exactly the same.
Okay, they had exactly the same characteristics, the 80-day fetus of the
girl and the 40-day fetus of the boy, and presumably it wasn't
not developing at all for 40 days. So because they had exactly
the same characteristics, we could assume that those are the same. So
anyway, this is the question about again, how do they know boy
or girl if you can't tell at that early age? But it
is an interesting way that they're... can you explain that? Yeah. The
Gemara's saying, so okay, you looked at the girl fetus according to
Rabbi Ishmael and you said, look, 81 days, it's developed. You see
it develops in 81 days. But no, you know it's developed in
81 days, but you don't know it wasn't developed in 41 days.
So the answer is no, because the stage of development at 81
for the girl was exactly the same stage as at 40 for
the boy. That's at least what the assertion is. Okay, so that's
the question...
what? I think you'd have a twist that they're in discrepancy.
No, by the time... no, I mean it's developing, it's just, it's
just a different pace of development in the womb.
That's possible. That's theoretically possible.
Because based on the XY, you mean?
Yeah, but it's... all right, I mean this is a very interesting
way that they're dealing with
outside evidence.
Yeah, there's a lot of...
so what to do?
Right, there are Gemaras sometimes that they treat outside evidence, you know,
legitimately. Sometimes they are offended by the very, as you said, use
of empirical evidence. This Gemara is somewhere in the middle, because it's
actually saying maybe it's not a great proof. Like it seems more
open to the possibility of using it if you could bring solid
evidence.
Right, it's the question that they, that it's an imbecile and I'm
giving you a puzzle so don't bother me, or is the question
that there's a flaw in the experiment.
Right, exactly. Exactly and both of those are indicated by the phrase
אני מביא ראיה מן הפסוק ani meivi ra'aya min hapasuk basically says
I'm quoting פסוקים pesukim don't talk to me about other stuff, and
the other was אין מביאין ראיה מן השוטים ein meivi'in ra'aya min
hashotim which means that the experiment wasn't done well. Right, and where
the גמרא holds there are, there's a lot of this is one
of the cases but there are many cases and I understand. I
understand and there's an ambivalence about that. Okay, there's not one answer
to that. There definitely is an ambivalence, רבי. Rabbi. Let's read, let's
get a little bit further. Okay. וחכמים אומרים ארבעים ואחד לזכר וארבעים
ואחד לנקבה. Vachachamim omrim arba’im ve’echad lazachar ve’arba’im ve’echad lankevah. וחכמים היינו
תנא קמא, Vachachamim haynu tanna kamma, isn't that the תנא קמא? tanna
kamma? We said 41 days and the rabbis responded back to רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael boy or girl 41 days. וכי תימא למסתמא רישא
כרבנן דיחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים, Vachi teima lemistama reisha kerabbanan deyachid verabbim
halacha kerabbim,
maybe it's to let you know that the סתם stam opinion in
the beginning was the חכמים, chachamim, was the majority opinion so you
know to פסקן pasken like the חכמים. chachamim. פשיטא, pshita, of course!
So, I mean of course you would go like the first, like
the סתם stam opinion.
מהו דתימא אימא מסתברא טעמיה דרבי ישמעאל. mahu deteima eima mistavra tameih
deRabbi Yishmael. Maybe רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael's position makes sense. דקמסייע ליה
קרא, dekamsaya lei kra, I mean at least he gives some meaning
otherwise nobody knows why is a girl 80 days and a boy
40 days in terms of the טומאה וטהרה? tumah vetaharah? Right? It's
the first thing you ask when you are learning פרשת תזריע. parshat
Tazria. Why is the טומאה והטהרה tumah vehataharah of a girl double
that of a boy? So, so he gives you a reason. So
maybe we should פסקן pasken like it. קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that no, even with the פסוק pasuk we rule like the
חכמים. chachamim. Let's take a look.
But isn't it a rule? This isn't this is a fact.
Of course it's a rule. If a woman miscarries on day 60
and it's a girl, does she have טומאת לידה? tumat leidah?
That's the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay. Now, דרש רבי שמלאי למה
הולד דומה במעי אמו? darash Rabbi Simlai lema havlad domeh bimei immo?
To what is the infant like in its mother's womb?
לפנקס שמקופל ומונח. lepinkas shemekupal umunach. So like a פנקס, pinkas, like
a ledger, you know, like two hard, like two, anyways, stiff boards
that's folded over. ידיו על שתי צדעיו, yadav al shtei tzad'av, the
hands are on its temples.
שתי אציליו על שתי ארכובותיו, shtei atzilav al shtei arkubotav, its elbows
are by its knees. ב' עקביו על ב' עגבותיו, bet ekevav al
bet agvotov, the ankles are tucked in by the buttocks. וראשו מונח
לו בין ברכיו, verosho munach lo bein birkav, and the head is
between its thighs. It's pretty descriptive of what a fetus looks like
in the womb. ופיו סתום וטיבורו פתוח. upiv satum vetiburo patuach. The
mouth is closed and the navel is open. Okay, that's where it's
getting from the umbilical cord. ואוכל ממה שאמו אוכלת, ve’ochel mimmah she’immo
ochelet, it eats what its mother eats, it comes through the umbilical
cord. ושותה ממה שאמו שותה, vessoteh mimmah she’immo shotah, and drinks what
its mother drinks, so don't drink alcohol. ואינו מוציא רעי, ve’eino motzi
re’i, and it does not defecate.
That's the whole amniotic fluid.
Okay, how does a fetus defecate? What happens? It gets dissolved by
it,
that's the whole amniotic fluid.
Oh, it is? It's like neutralized.
It's all No, that's it's the excretion.
It is the excretion. How does the excretion not have negative, like
poison? It's just not. No, it's because it's contained in the whole
sac. I see. Okay. Anyway, so it says that it says that
alright, it says it does not excrete. שמא יהרוג את אמו, shema
yaharog et immo, because if it would excrete that would flow back
into the mother's bloodstream, it understands, and kill the mother. וכיון שיצא
לאויר העולם, vekeivan sheyatza la’avir ha’olam, and once it's born, נפתח הסתום,
niftach hasatum, what was closed opened, the mouth opened. ונסתם הפתוח, venistam
hapatuach, what was open closed, the umbilical cord, the navel.
שאילמלא כן, she’ilmalei ken, and if that hadn't happened, אינו יכול לחיות
אפילו שעה אחת, eino yachol lichyot afilu sha’ah achat, it could not
live even for one second, which is why we say in the
אשר יצר, Asher Yatzar, you know, that we have holes and closed
things and open things and if one we couldn't live for one
second. Some people say what do you mean can't live for one
second? You close your mouth for a second. So it says well,
what it means maybe one explanation is no, no, as a fetus,
if the wrong things were open and closed it would have died
instantly. All right, anyway, but that's all based on the ברכה, berachah,
that's the base of the ברכה berachah of אשר יצר. Asher Yatzar.
Let me just read a little bit more. ונר דלוק לו על
ראשו, vener daluk lo al rosho, while it's in the womb, there's
a candle over its head, I assume not a literal candle, some
light over its head. וצופה ומביט מסוף העולם ועד סופו, vetzofeh umabit
missof ha’olam ve’ad sofo, the fetus in the womb can see from
one end of the world to the next. שנאמר בהלו נרו עלי
ראשי לאורו אלך חשך, shenne’emar behillo nero alei roshi le’oro elech choshech,
God's candle was over my head, through its light I will go
in the darkness. בהלו? behillo? I'm not sure. It's a what particle
word? It doesn't have a clear... ואל תתמה, ve’al titmah, do not
be astounded that how could you say a fetus could look from
one end of the world to the next? שהרי אדם ישן כאן
ורואה חלום באספמיא, sheharei adam yashen kan vero’eh chalom be’aspamya, a man
could be sleeping sleeping and have a dream about Spain. So the
fetus could see places that are outside of its eyesight.
ואין לך ימים שאדם שרוי בטובה יותר מאותן הימים. ve’ein lecha yamim
she’adam sharui betovah yoter me’otan hayamim. Right? There are no days there
are no days that are so much immersed in goodness as the
days that the fetus is in its mother's womb. שנאמר מי יתנני
כירחי קדם כימי אלוה ישמרני, shenne’emar mi yittneni keyerachei kedem kiyemei elo’ah
yishmereni, who would give me like the months of old, like the
days that God like the days that God will watch me.
ואיזו ימים שיש בהם ירחים ואין בהם שנים. ve’eizu yamim sheyesh bahem
yerachim ve’ein bahem shanim. The months of old? What's a period of
time that only has months and no years? הוי אומר אלו ירחי
לידה Hevei omeir eilu yerachei leida the months of childbirth, there are
no years because it's only going to be nine months. ומלמדין אותו
כל התורה כולה U-melamdin oto kol ha-Torah kullah and you've heard this
מדרש midrash before. They teach the infant all of the תורה. Torah.
שנאמר ויורני ויאמר לי יתמך דברי לבך שמור מצוותי וחיה She-neemar v'yoreini
v'yomer li yitmoch devari libecha shemor mitzvotai ve-chyeh and God taught me
and said to me support my, hold fast to my words, your
heart, observe my commandments and live. ואומר V'omeir the פסוק pasuk says...
Is that baby true?
Apparently, not making a distinction. בסוד אלוה עלי אהלי Be-sod eloka alai
oholi which is with the secret of God sort of hovering over
me or, you know, protecting over me, my tent. מאי ואומר Mai
v'omeir why a second פסוק? pasuk? וכי תימא נביא הוא דקאמר V'chi
teima navi hu de-ka'amar maybe the נביא navi is saying God taught
me, it's not talking about the fetus. תא שמע בסוד אלוה
עלי אהלי Ta shema be-sod eloka alai oholi and that פסוק pasuk
about the secret of God's secrets is the end of that פסוק
pasuk of the months of old, which we said was when the
fetus was in the womb.
Everything the fetus knows is in the womb?
Because of the months of old, מי יתנני כירחי קדם. Mi yitneini
k'yarchei kedem. Yeah, it's part of the same
פסוק. pasuk. וכיון שבא לאויר העולם Ve-keivan she-ba l'avir ha-olam and when
he comes to the world, בא מלאך וסטרו על פיו ba malach
u-satoro al piv an angel comes and smacks him on his mouth,
ומשכחו כל התורה כולה u-mashkachu kol ha-Torah kullah and makes him forget
the entire תורה. Torah. שנאמר לפתח חטאת רובץ She-neemar l'petach chatat roveitz
that he that the sin is hovering by the opening. So as
soon as you get into the imperfect world, you're in this perfect
world of the womb, you can see from one end to the
world, you know all the תורה, Torah, and then you have to
enter into the world of imperfection and the world of sin and
you lose your תורה Torah and you have to struggle to get
it back, and we will continue with this struggle where we really
have to end in the middle of it but we'll continue with
it tomorrow.